上一节我们讨论了模逆，我们说过
In the previous segment we talked about
modular inversion and we said the Euclid's
欧几里德算法给了我们一个有效的找元素的模N逆的方法
algorithm gives us an efficient way to
find the inverse of an element modulo N.
本节我们沿着历史往后看
In this segment we're going to forward
through time and we're going to move to
来到17、17世纪，我们来讨论
the seventeenth and eighteenth century
where we're going to talk about
费马和欧拉的贡献。在这之前我们先简单回顾一下
Fermat and Euler contributions.
Before that let's do a quick review of
上一节讨论的内容。通常我用N表示
what we discussed in the previous segment.
So as usual I'm going to let N denote the
正整数，我们说N正好是一个n位整数
positive integer and let's just say that N
happens to be a n-bit integer, in other
换句话说，N在2^n和2^(n+1)之间，通常
words it's between two to the n and two to
the n+1, as usual we're going to let P
我们记质数为p。现在我们说过Z_N是
denote a prime. Now we said that
ZN is a set of integers from zero
从0到N-1的全体整数集，我们说过，我们可以
在这个模N集上进行加法和乘法
to N-1 and we said that we can add and
multiply elements in the set modulo N. We
我们也说过Z_N^*是Z_N中全体可逆元素的集合
also said that ZN star is basically the
set of invertible elements in ZN. And we
我们证明了一个简单的引理，X是可逆的
当且仅当X与N互质
proved a simple lemma to say that, X is
invertible if and only if X is relatively
我们不仅完全理解了什么元素是可逆的
prime to N. And not only did we
completely understand which elements are
哪些不是，我们也展示了一个非常有效的算法
invertible and which aren't, we also
showed a very efficient algorithm based on
基于扩展的欧几里德算法，去找到Z_N中X的逆
Euclid's extended algorithm, to find the
inverse of an element X in ZN. And we said
我们说过这个算法的运行时间是O(n^2)
that the running time of this algorithm,
is basically order n squared, where
n是N的位数。如我所说
again, n is the number of bits of the
number capital N. So as I said, now
(位数显然是O(log(N))的)
现在我们要从古希腊时代来到17世纪
we're going to move from Greek times all
the way to the seventeenth century and
讨论费马。费马提出了很多重要的定理
talk about Fermat. So Fermat did a number
of important theorems. The one that I want
我今天想给大家看的如下。假设我给大家一个质数p
to show you here today is the following.
So suppose I give you a prime P. Then in
然后事实上对Z_p^*里的任意元素X，如果我研究
fact for any element X in ZP star, it so
happens that if I look at X and raise it
X^(p-1)，我在Z_p中就会得到1。那么我们来看一个简单例子
to the power of P - 1, I'm a gonna get
one, in ZP. So let's look at a quick
假设我设p=5。我看3^(p-1)
example. Suppose I set the number P to be
five. And I look at, three to the power of
换句话说，3的4次方，3^4=81
P-1. In other words, three to the power of
four, Three to the power of four is 81,
事实上81=1 mod 5。这个例子满足费马小定理
which in fact, is one modulo five. This
example satisfies Fermat's theorem.
有趣的是，费马并没有自己证明这个定理
Interestingly, Fermat actually didn't prove this theorem himself. The proof
证明实际上要等到欧拉在100年后给出
actually waited until Euler, who
proved that almost 100 years later. And in
事实上，他证明了这个定理的一个更一般的版本
fact, he proved a much more general
version of this theorem. So let's look at
我们看费马小定理的一个简单应用。
假设我看Z_p^*里的一个元素X
a simple application of Fermat's theorem.
Suppose I look at an element X in Z P
我想提醒大家，这里的p必须是质数
star. And I want to remind you here that P
must be a prime. Well, then what do we
我们知道什么？我们知道X^(p-1)=1。我们可以写
know? We know that X to the P minus one is
equal to one. Well, we can write X to the
X^(p-1)=X*X^(p-2)。那么现在我们知道了
P minus one as X times X to the power of P
minus two. Well so now we know that X
X乘以X的p-2次方正好是1
times X to the power of P minus two
happens to be equal to one. And what that
这就是说，X模p的逆正好就是X^(p-2)
says, is that really the inverse of X
modulo P, is simply X to the P minus two.
这就给了我们另一个计算X模质数的逆的算法
So this gives us another algorithm for
finding the inverse of X modulo a prime.
计算X^(p-2)，就会得到X的逆
Simply raise X to the power of p minus
two, and that will give us the inverse of
实际上这是一个计算模质数的逆的好方法
x. It turns out, actually this is a fine
way to compute inverses modulo a prime.
但是与欧几里德算法相比有两个不足。首先
But it has two deficiencies compared to
Euclid's algorithm. First of all, it only
他只能工作在质数模上，而欧几里德算法
也能工作在合数模上
works modulo primes, Whereas, Euclid's
algorithm worked modulo composites as
第二，实际上这个算法效率更低
well. And second of all, it turns out this
algorithm is actually less efficient. When
当我们讨论然后计算模指数时
we talk about how to do modular
exponentiations--we're gonna do that in
我们在本章最后一节讨论之。大家会看到
计算这个指数的运行时间
the last segment in this module--you'll
see that the running time to compute this
实际上是p长度的立方。所以这会花掉大约
exponentiation is actually cubic in the
size of P. So this will take roughly log
(log p)^3的时间，如果大家记得，欧几里德算法
cube of P, whereas if you remember,
Euclid's algorithm was able to compute the
可以计算逆，在p长度的平方的时间内
inverse in quadratic time in the
representation of P. So not only is this
所以这个算法不仅不普适，它仅限质数模；而且更低效
algorithm less general it only works for
primes, it's also less efficient. So score
所以欧几里德赢了。但是这个关于质数的事实极为重要
one for Euclid. But nevertheless, this
fact about primes is extremely important,
我们将在未来几周大量用到这个事实
and we're gonna be making extensive use of
it in the next couple of weeks. So let me
我给大家看一个简单的费马小定理的应用
show you a quick and simple application
for Fermat's theorem suppose we wanted
假设我们想生成一个随机的大质数，比如说
我们的质数需要有1000位长
to generate a large random prime, say our
prime needed to be 1,000 bits or so. So
我们要找的质数是2的1024次方的量级
the prime we're looking for is on the
order of two to the 1024. So here's
这是一个非常简单的概率问题。我们可以选择一个
a very simple probabilistic algorithm.
What we would do is we would choose a
随机整数，从一个指定的区间里面。然后我们检测
random integer in the interval that was
specified. And then we would test whether
这个选取的整数是不是满足费马小定理。
换句话说，我们可以用2为底数进行检测
this integer satisfies Fermat's theorem.
In other words, we would test for example
我们检测2的p-1次方是否在Z_p中等于1
using the base two; we would test whether
two to the power of p minus one equals one
如果答案是否定的，如果这个等式不成立，那么我们知道
in Z p. If the answer is no, then if this
equality doesn't hold, then we know for
我们选择的这个数p一定不是质数。如果这个发生了
sure that the number p that we chose is
not a prime. And if that happens, all we
我们只需要返回第一步，尝试另一个数
do is we go back to step one and we try
another prime. And we do this again and
我们一次次地这么做，直到我们最终找到一个整数
满足费马小定理的条件
again and again, until finally we find an
integer that satisfies this condition. And
我们一旦找到了一个整数满足这个条件，我们就输出它
once we find an integer that satisfies
this condition, we simply output it and
然后停止。实际上，虽然很难证明
stop. Now it turns out, this is actually a
fairly difficult statement to prove. But
但如果一个随机数通过了这里的检测，那么它极有可能
it turns out if a random number passes
this test, then it's extremely likely to
是质数。特别地，p不是质数的概率非常小
be a prime. In particular the probability
that P is not a prime is very small. It's
对于1024位的数来说，不是质数的概率小于2^-60
like less than two to the -60 for the
range of 1024 bit numbers. As the
随着数的变大，一个数通过这里的测试
number gets bigger and bigger the
probability that it passes this test here,
却不是质数的概率迅速向0衰减
but is not a prime drops to zero very
quickly. So this is actually quite an
所以这是个很有趣的算法。大家发现，我们
无法保证输出一定是质数
interesting algorithm. You realize we're
not guaranteed that the output is in fact
我们只知道它非常有可能是一个质数。换句话说
a prime. All we know is that it's very,
very likely to be a prime. In other words
它不是质数的唯一可能，是我们极其倒霉
the only way that it's not a prime is that
we got extremely unlucky. In fact so
事实上倒霉到一个可忽略的概率事件发生了
unlucky that a negligible probability
event just happened. Another way to say
另一种说法是，如果你看所有1024位的整数的集合
this is that if you look at the set of all
1024 integers, then, well, there's the set
然后有质数的集合。我把质数写在这。然后
of primes. Let me write prime here. And
then there is a small number of
有很少量的会导致检测失败的合数。我们把假质数记为F
composites that actually will falsify the
test. Let's call them F for false primes.
我们记它们为FP，假质数的意思。
有很少的数，不是质数，是合数的
Let's call them FP, for false primes.
There's a very small number of composites
却能通过这个检测的。但是当我们选择随机整数时
that are not prime and yet will pass this
test. But as we choose random integers,
我们选择一个在这，一个在这，一个在这，等等。。
you know, we choose one here, one here,
one here, and so on, as we choose random
我们选择随机整数时，落到假质数集合里的概率
integers, the probability that we fall
into the set of false primes is so small
如此之小，以至于这是一个可忽略的时间。换句话说
That it's essentially a negligible event
that we can ignore. In other words, one
可以证明假质数的集合是极小的
can prove that the set of false primes is
extremely small, and a random choice is
(实际上这种假质数叫Carmichael数，其分布密度指数级衰减)
随机选择不太可能选到假质数。现在我应该提到
unlikely to pick such a false prime. Now I
should mention, in fact, this is a very
这是生成质数的一个非常简单的算法。
目前来看，这还不是最好的算法
simple algorithm for generating primes.
It's actually, by far, not the best
我们现在有了更好的算法。事实上，你一旦有了
algorithm. We have much better algorithms
now. And, in fact, once you have a
一个候选的质数，我们现在有非常有效的算法
candidate prime, we now have very
efficient algorithms that will actually
可以证明这个候选质数确实是一个质数
prove beyond a doubt that this candidate
prime really is a prime. So we don't even
我们甚至不需要依赖于概率的结果。
但是，这个费马检测如此简单
have to rely on probabilistic statements.
But nevertheless, this Fermat test is so
我只想为大家展示，这是一个容易生成质数的方法
simple, that I just wanted to show you
that it's an easy way to generate primes.
尽管在实际中，并不用这个方法来生成质数
Although in reality, this is not how
primes are generated. As the last point,
最后，我要说，大家可能想知道这个迭代需要重复多少次
I'll say that you might be wondering how
many times this iteration has to repeat
直到我们找到质数。有一个经典的结果
until we actually find the prime. And
that's actually a classic result; it's
叫做质数定理，这个定理是说，经过几百次迭代
called the prime number theorem, which
says that, after a few hundred iterations,
(迭代次数的期望是1024 ln 2，约为710)
我们就能以很高的概率找到质数。那么从期望来看
in fact, we'll find the prime with
high probability. So in expectation, one would
可能需要几百次的迭代，无需更多了
expect a few hundred iterations and no
more. Now that we understand
现在我们理解了费马小定理，接下来我想讨论
Fermat's theorem, the next thing I want
to talk about is what's called the
Z_p^*的结构。我们看在这之后100年。。
structure of ZP star. So here, we are
going to move 100 years into the future...
18世纪，看欧拉的工作。欧拉证明的最初结果之一
Into the eighteenth century and look at
the work of Euler. And one of the first
用现代语言来讲，Z_p^*是一个
things Euler showed is in modern language
is that ZP star is what's called a
循环群。Z_p^*是一个循环群是什么意思？
cyclic group. What does it mean that ZP
star is a cyclic group? What it means is
这意味着Z_p^*里有某个元素g，如果我们取g
that there exists some element G in ZP
star, such that if we take G and raise to
计算g的一组幂，g^2，g^3，g^4。。
a bunch of powers G, G squared, G cubed, G
to the fourth. And so on and so forth up
直到g^(p-2)。注意没有点超过g^(p-2)
until we reach G to the P minus two.
Notice there's no point of going beyond G
因为根据费马小定理，g^(p-1)=1
to the p minus two, because G to the p
minus one by Fermat's theorem is equal to
所以我们回到了1。如果我们回到g^(p-1)
one, so then we will cycle back to one. If
we go back to G to the p minus one, then G
那么g^p=g，g^(p+1)=g^2，等等。。
to the p will be equal to G, G to the p
plus one will be equal to G squared, and
我们就得到了一个循环，如果我们继续增加g的指数
so on and so forth. So we'll actually get
a cycle if we keep raising to higher and
我们也可以就停在g^(p-2)
higher powers of G. So we might as well
stop at the power of G to the p minus two.
欧拉证明了事实上，有这么一个元素g
And what Euler showed is that in fact
there is an element G such that if you
如果你看它的所有幂，可以扩展成整个群Z_p^*
look at all of its powers all of its
powers expand the entire group ZP Star.
g的幂给出了Z_p^*里的所有元素
The powers of G give us all the elements
in ZP star. Elements of this, of this type
这样的元素g叫做生成元。那么g就叫做Z_p^*的一个生成元
is called a generator. So G would be said
to be a generator of ZP star. So let's
我们看一个简单例子。例如，p=7
look at a quick example. So let's look,
for example, at P equals seven. And let's
我们看3的所有幂。3^2, 3^3, 3^4
look at all the powers of three. So three
squared three cubed, three to the fourth,
3^5, 3^6，由费马小定理，我们已经知道
three to the fifth, Three to the six,
already we know, is equal to one modular
3^6=1 mod 7。所以没有必要看3^6了
seven by Fermat's Theorem. So there's no
point in looking at three to the six. We
我们知道了它会是1。这里我给大家计算了所有这些幂
know we would just get one. So here, I
calculated all these powers for you, and I
我写下了它们，大家可以看到我们得到了Z_7^*里
wrote them out. And you see that in fact,
we get all the numbers in Z,
所有的数。换句话说，我们获得了1,2,3,4,5,6
in Z7 star. In other words, we get
one, two, three, four, five, and six. So
所以我们说，3是Z_7^*的一个生成元。现在我应该指出
we would say that three is a generator of
Z7 star. Now I should point out that not
不是每个元素都是生成元。例如，如果我们看2的所有幂
every element is a generator. For example,
if we look at all the powers of two, well,
那不会生成整个群。特别地，如果我们看2^0
that's not gonna generate the entire
group. In particular, if we look at two to
会得到1，2^1=2, 2^2=4
the zero, we get one. Two to the one, we
get two. Two squared is four, and two
2^3=8=1 mod 7。所以我们循环回来了
cubed is eight, which is one modular
seven. So we cycled back and then two to
那么2^4=2, 2^5=4..等等
the fourth would be two, two to the fifth
would be four. And so on and so forth. So
那么如果我们看2的各个幂，我们只能获得1, 2, 4
if we look at the powers of two, we just
get one, two, and four. We don't get the
我们不能获得整个群，因此我们说2不是Z_7^*的生成元
whole group and therefore we say that two
is not a generator of Z7 star. Now again,
一个很常用的是，给定Z_p^*里的一个元素g
something that we'll use very often is
given an element G of ZP, if we look at a
如果我们看g的全体幂组成的集合，得到的集合
就叫做g的生成群
set of all powers of G, the resulting set
is gonna be called the group generated by
这些都是g的幂
G, okay? So these are all the powers of G.
They give us what's called a
它们给了我们一个乘法群。这些技术术语并不重要
multiplicative group. Again, the technical
term doesn't matter. The point is we're
重要的是，我们把所有这些g的幂，叫做g的生成群
gonna call all these powers of G, the
group generated by G. In fact there's this
事实上这个记号我们不会经常使用：
notation which I don't use very often,
angle G angle, to denote this group that's
表示g的生成群。然后，我们把g的生成群的大小
generated by G. And then we call the order
of G in Z p star, we simply let that be
叫做g在Z_p^*里的阶。换句话说
the size of the group that's generated by
G. So in other words, the order of G in Z
g在Z_p^*里的阶等于的大小。另一种思考的方法是
p star is the size of this group. But
another way to think about that is
g的阶是满足在Z_p中，g^a=1的最小的整数a
basically it's the smallest integer A such
that G to the A is equal to one in Z P.
是最小的次数，导致g的幂等于1
Okay, it's basically the smallest power
that causes the power of G to be equal to
非常容易看出这个等式，如果我们看g的所有幂
one. And it's very easy to see that this
equality here basically if we look at all
我们看1, g, g^2, g^3..
the powers of G and we look at one, G, G
squared, G cubed and so on and so forth up
直到我们得到g^(||-1)。然后如果我们看
until we get to G to the order of G minus
one. And then if we look at the order of G
g^||，根据定义，g^||=1
to the order of G. This thing is simply
going to be equal to one, by definition.
好，再看更高的点没有意义了
Okay, so there's no point in looking at
any higher powers. We might as well just
这里我们可以停止升幂次了。因此这个集合的大小
stop raising to powers here. And as a
result the size of the set, in fact, is
事实上就是g的阶。大家可以看到这个阶是最小的幂次
the order of G. And you can see that the
order is the smallest power such that
满足对应的g的幂在Z_p中等于1。那么我希望说清楚了
raising G to that power gives us one in Z
p. So I hope this is clear although it
理解所有的这些记号需要费些功夫
might take a little bit of thinking to
absorb all this notation. But in the
同时我们看几个例子。我们固定质数为7
meantime let's look at a few examples. So,
again, let's fix our, our prime to be
我们看其各个元素的阶
seven. And let's look at the order of the
number of elements. So what is the order
3模7的阶是多少？我们在问3模7的生成群的大小
of three modulus of seven? Well, we're
asking what is the size of the group that
我们说过，3是Z_7^*的一个生成元
three generates modulus of seven? Well, we
said that three is a generator of Z7 star.
所以它生成了Z_7^*的全部元素。Z_7^*里共有6个元素
So it generates all of Z7 star. There are
six elements in Z7 star. And therefore we
所以3的阶等于6。类似地，我可以问
say that the order of three is equal to
six. Similarly, I can ask, well, what is
2模7的阶是多少？事实上，我们已经见过答案了
the order of two modulo seven? And in
fact, we already saw the answer. So let's,
我问大家，2模7的阶是多少？看看大家能否解出答案
I'll ask you, what is the order of two
modulo seven and see if you can figure
那么答案是3，原因是如果我们看
out what this answer is. So the answer is
three and again, the reason is if we look
2模7的幂组成的集合，我们有1,2,2^2
at the set of powers of two modulo seven,
we have one, two, two squared, and then
然后2^3就又是1了。所以这些就是2模7的所有幂
two cubed is already equal to one. So this
is the entire set of powers of two modulo
只有3个，因此2模7的阶是3
seven. There are only three of them and,
therefore, the order of two modulo seven
我问大家一个有点难的问题：1模7的阶是多少？
is exactly three. Now let me ask you a
trick question. What's the order of one
答案是1，因为大家看1的生成群
modulo seven? Well, the answer is one.
Because if you look at the group that's
只有一个数在1的生成群里，即数1
generated by one, well, there's only one
number in that group, namely the number
如果我计算1的一组幂，我总是得到1
one. If I raise one to a whole bunch of
powers, I'm always gonna get one, And
所以1模7的阶是1，事实上，1模任意质数的阶
therefore the order of 1 modulo 7
In fact the order of 1 modulo any prime
总是1。现在有重要的拉格朗日定理
is always gonna be 1. Now there's an
important theorem of Lagrange, that
我这里说的仅仅是拉格朗日定理的一个特例
actually this is a very, very special case
of it, what I am stating here. But
(定理说：有限子群的阶必然整除有限群的阶)
拉格朗日定理意味着，如果你看g模p的阶
Langrage's theorem basically implies that
if you look at the order of G modulo p,
这个阶始终整除p-1。那么在我们给大家的两个例子中
the order is always going to divide P-1. So in our two example you see,
6整除7-1，即6整除6，类似地，3整除7-1
six divides seven minus one, six divides
six, and similarly, three divides seven
即3整除6。但这是很一般的
minus one. Namely again three divides six.
But this is very general; your order is
你的阶始终是p-1的因子。事实上，我会告诉你
always going be a factor of P minus one.
In fact, I'll tell you, maybe it's a
也许你可以想想这个谜题：由拉格朗日定理的这个事实
puzzle for you to think about. It's
actually very easy to deduce Fermat's
非常容易推导出费马小定理
theorem directly from this fact, from this
Lagrange's theorem in fact. And so
(显然，费马小定理等式的左边只能是若干个1相乘)
所以费马小定理某种意义上是拉格朗日定理的直接推论
Fermat's theorem really in some sense
follows directly from Lagrange's theorem.
顺便一提，拉格朗日的工作在19世纪，大家看到
Lagrange, by the way, did his work in the
nineteenth century, so you can already see
我们是如何沿着历史前进的。我们从古希腊时代出发
how we're making progress through time. We
started in Greek times, and already we
现在已经到了19世纪了。我可以告诉大家
ended up in the nineteenth century. And I
can tell you that more advanced crypto
更高级的密码学实际上用了大量的20世纪的数学
actually uses twentieth century math very
extensively. Now that we understand the
现在我们理解了Z_p^*的结构，我们把它推广到合数
structure of ZP star, let's generalize
that to composites, and look at the
来看Z_N^*的结构。那么我这里想展示给大家的是
structure of ZN star. So what I wanna show
you here is what's called Euler's Theorem
欧拉定理，一个费马小定理的直接推广
which is a, a direct generalization of
Fermat's Theorem. So, Euler defined the
那么欧拉定义了下面这个函数，那么给定一个整数N，
欧拉定义了函数ψ
following function. So given an integer N,
he defined what's called the phi
ψ(M)，表示Z_N^*的大小
function, phi of M, to be
basically the size of the set ZN star.
有时这也叫做欧拉的ψ函数，Z_N^*的大小
This is sometimes called, Euler's phi
function. The size of the set Z N star. So
例如，我们已经看了Z_12^*。我们说过Z_12^*
for example, we already looked at Z twelve
star. We said that Z twelve star contains
包含4个元素：1,5,7,11，因此我们说
these four elements, one, five, seven, and
eleven. And therefore we say that phi of
ψ(12)=4。那么我问大家一个问题，ψ(p)是多少？
twelve is simply the number four. So let
me ask you as a puzzle, what is phi of P?
也就是Z_p^*的大小。那么事实上，我们说过
It will basically be the size of Z P star.
And so, in fact, we said that in the Z P
Z_p^*包含了Z_p中的全部元素，除了0。因此
star contains all of Z P except for the
number zero. And therefore, phi of P for
对于任意质数p，ψ(p)=p-1。现在，有一个特例
any prime P is gonna be P minus one. Now,
there is a special case, which I'm gonna
我这里要说，之后在RSA系统中我们要用到
state here and we're gonna use later for
the RSA system. If N happens to be a
如果N正好是两个质数p和q的乘积，那么
ψ(N)=N-p-q+1
product of two primes, then phi of N is
simply N minus P minus Q plus one. And let
我来为大家解释为什么是这样。N是Z_N的大小
me just show you why that's true. So
basically N is the size of Z N. And now we
现在我们需要移除所有与m不是互质的元素
need to remove all the elements that are
not relatively prime to m. Well how can an
一个元素如何才能不与m互质呢？
它要不被p整除，要不就被q整除
element not be relatively prime to m? It's
gotta be divisible by p or it's gotta be
在0到m-1之间，有多少元素
divisible by q. Well how many elements
between zero and m minus one are there,
能被p整除？一定有q个
there that are divisible by p? Well there
are exactly q of them. How many elements
有多少元素能被q整除？一定有p个
are there that are divisible by q? Well
there are exactly p of them. So we
那么我们减去p，来除去那些被q整除的数；
减去q，来除去那些被p整除的数
subtract p to get rid of those divisible
by q. We subtract q to get rid of those
大家注意，我们见了0两次，因为
divisible by p. And you notice we
subtracted zero twice, because zero is
0被p和q同时整除，所以我们再加1
divisible both by P and Q. And therefore,
we add one just to make sure we subtract
以确保我们只减了一次0。不难看出
ψ(N)=N-p-q+1
zero only once. And so it's not difficult
to see that phi(N) is N-P-Q+1. And another way
另一种书写方法是(p-1)(q-1)。好，那么
这是我们待会将利用的事实
of writing that is simply (P-1) times (Q-1). Okay,
so this is a fact that we will use later
当我们回来讨论RSA系统时。目前只是定义了
on, when we come back and talk about the
RSA system. So far, this is just defining
欧拉的ψ函数。但现在欧拉非常好地运用了这个ψ函数
this phi function of Euler. But now Euler
put this phi function to really good use.
他证明了这个惊人的事实
And what he proved is this amazing fact
here that basically says that if you give
如果你给我Z_N^*中任意的元素X，事实上，X的ψ(N)次方
me any element X in Z N star. In fact, and
it so happens that X to the power of phi(N)
在Z_N中一定等于1。那么大家可以看出，
这是费马小定理的一个推广
is equal to one in Z N. So you can see
that this is a generalization of Fermat's
特别地，费马小定理只适用于质数的情况
theorem; in particular, Fermat's theorem
only applied to primes. For primes we know
对于质数而言，我们知道ψ(p)=p-1。
换句话说，如果N是质数
that phi(p) is equal to p minus one, and
in other words if N were prime we would
我们在这里写下p-1，那么我们就得到了费马小定理
simply write p minus one here, and then we
would get exactly Fermat's theorem. The
欧拉定理的美丽之处在于，他适用于合数
beauty of Euler's theorem is that it
applies to composites, and not just
不仅仅是质数。那么我们看一些例子。
我们看5的ψ(12)次方
primes. So let's look at some examples. So
let's look at five to the power of phi(12).
那么5是Z_12^*里的元素。如果我们计算5的ψ(12)次方
So five is an element of Z12 star.
If we raise it to the power of phi of
我们应该得到1。我们知道ψ(12)=4
twelve, we should be getting one. Well, we
know that phi(12) is 4, so we're
那么我们计算5^4，是625
raising 5 to the power of 4. Five to
the power of four is 625 and it's a simple
容易计算出625等于1模12
calculation to show that that's equal to
1 modulo 12. So this is proof
这是一个例证，但当然不是证明，仅仅是个例子
by example but of course it's not a proof
at all. It's just an example. But in fact
但事实上不难证明欧拉定理。事实上，我会告诉大家，
it's not difficult to prove Euler's
theorem and in fact I'll tell you that
欧拉定理也是拉格朗日定理的特例
Euler's theorem is also a very special
case of Lagrange's general theorem.
好，那么我们说这是费马定理的推广
Okay so we say that this is a
generalization of Fermat's theorem and
事实上我们会看到，欧拉定理是RSA密码系统的基础
in fact as we'll see this Euler's
theorem is the basis of the RSA crypto
我先讲这么多，下节继续讨论
system. So I stop here and we continue
with modular quadratic equations in the
模二次方程
next segment.